大卫·爱登堡：这是入口
DAVID ATTENBOROUGH: This is the entrance
到最伟大的自然奇观之一。
to one of the greatest of natural wonders.
韩松洞，越南。
Hang Son Doong, in Vietnam.
它被认为是地球上最大的洞穴。
It's thought to be the largest cave on Earth.
在这里，地下200米处，
Here, 200 metres underground,
一年中只有几周的时间，
for just a few weeks a year,
阳光透过洞穴顶部的一个洞照射进来。
sunbeams cast light through a hole in the cave's
光线刚刚好
There is just enough light
使植物能够生长。
to enable plants to grow.
但更深入的旅行，
But travel deeper,
黑暗又回来了。
and darkness returns.
而你达到了极限
And you reach the limit
生命可以存在的地方。
of where life can exist.
我们星球上这些最极端的地方
These most extreme places on our planet
往往是我们难以接触到的。
are often hard for us to reach.
事实上，这个洞穴是最近才发现的。
Indeed, this cave was only recently discovered.
它包含了许多惊喜。
And it contains many surprises.
洞穴珍珠
Cave pearls.
曾经微小的沙粒，
Once tiny sand grains,
现在球体有网球大小。
now spheres the size of tennis balls.
还有巨大的石笋...
And giant stalagmites...
..几个世纪以来形成
..formed over centuries
由数十亿个单独的水滴组成。
by billions of individual drops of water.
地下河流已雕刻
Underground rivers have carved
这条穿过石灰岩的伟大通道
this great passage through the limestone.
长超过五英里
Over five miles long
并且在某些地方足够宽
and wide enough in places
以容纳一架大型喷气式飞机。
to accommodate a jumbo jet.
而它就在这里，
And it is here,
在洞穴最远的房间里，
in the cave's furthest chamber,
那生命是可以找到的。
that life can be found.
半透明的洞穴鱼...
Translucent cave fish...
..还有虾。
..and shrimps.
与世隔绝千年，
Isolated for millennia,
其食物只不过是上面丛林中的营养物质。
feeding on little more than the nutrients from t
鱼完全瞎了
The fish are completely blind
并仅通过触摸就能找到路。
and find their way about by touch alone.
这些地下世界已经到了极限
These underground worlds are at the very limit
生命可以存在的地方。
of where life can exist.
但在地面之上，
But above ground,
我们星球上最极端的条件
our planet's most extreme conditions
发现于两极。
are found at the poles.
风声
WIND WHISTLES
在北方的这里，
Here in the north,
冬季气温可降至-50摄氏度。
winter temperatures can drop to -50 degrees Cels
一年中有四个月，
For four months of the year,
几乎没有一丝阳光。
there is barely a glimmer of sunlight.
但这里也一样，
But here, too,
生命找到了生存之道。
life finds a way to survive.
一群北极狼。
A pack of Arctic wolves.
它们浓密的皮毛保护了它们
Their dense fur has protected them
经历数月的严寒。
through months of bitter cold.
但现在太阳又回来了。
But now the sun is returning.
这是埃尔斯米尔岛。
This is Ellesmere Island.
短暂的夏季给了狼队重建实力的机会。
The short summer gives the wolves a chance to re
但在北极这里...
But here in the Arctic...
..生活从来都不容易。
..life is never easy.
这个群体由一位经验丰富的女性领导。
This pack is led by an experienced female.
如果她不能带他们去吃东西
If she can't lead them to food,
即将到来的冬天可能是他们的最后一个冬天。
the coming winter could be their last.
猎物分布在如此广阔的区域
Prey is spread over such a vast area
他们必须不断地移动......
that they must be constantly on the move...
..正在寻找它。
..in search of it.
但寻找猎物仅仅是开始。
But finding prey is only the beginning.
麝香牛。
Musk oxen.
它们的体型是狼的五倍。
They are five times the size of a wolf.
牛鼻息
OXEN SNORT
狼与牛的冲突由来已久，
The conflict between wolf and oxen is an ancient
自冰河时代以来就一直存在。
and has been waged since the Ice Age.
牛咕噜声
OXEN GRUNT
双方都知道对方的战术。
Each side knows the other's tactics.
狼群试图隔离
The wolves try to isolate
弱者或年轻人。
the weak or the young.
一头牛犊绊倒了……
A calf stumbles...
..狼群首领立即逼近。
..and the pack leader immediately closes in.
狼叫声
WOLF YELPS
但牛群重新集结，
But the herd regroups,
号角已准备就绪。
horns at the ready.
牛咕噜声
OXEN GRUNT
僵局。
Stalemate.
但它只能是简短的。
But it can only be brief.
这一次，牛群竞相向更高的地方跑去。
This time, the herd race to higher ground.
当他们到达山脊顶端时，
As they reach the top of the ridge,
雄性则转身自卫。
the males turn to defend themselves.
牛吼声
OXEN GROWL
僵局...
Stalemate...
..再次。
..again.
每一次失败的狩猎
Every unsuccessful hunt
使狼群变得虚弱。
leaves the pack weakened.
这可能是一顿更容易的饭菜。
This could be an easier meal.
狼嗅
WOLF SNIFFS
但有些不对劲。
But something is not right.
这只麝牛死于疾病。
This musk ox has died from a disease.
狼嗅嗅
WOLVES SNIFF
类似的疫情爆发变得越来越普遍
Outbreaks like this are becoming increasingly co
随着北极地区气候变暖。
as the climate warms across the Arctic.
尽管他们很饥饿，
Despite their hunger,
狼群不吃这具尸体。
the pack don't eat this carcass.
又一群。
Another herd.
包的另一个机会。
Another chance for the pack.
这一次，狼群成功地分裂了狼群。
This time, the wolves manage to split the herd.
这可能会增加他们的机会。
That may improve their chances.
女领头确保牛
The lead female makes sure that the oxen
不要再次到达山脊。
do not reach the ridge again.
少了一名后卫，小牛就更容易受到攻击。
With one less defender, the calf is more vulnera
牛犊叫声
OXEN CALF CALLS
非常需要的一顿饭。
A much-needed meal.
狼队必须继续发挥最大作用
The wolves must continue to make the most
夏天剩下的几周……
of the remaining weeks of summer...
..所以当冬天回来时
..so when winter returns
..他们已经准备好忍受
..they're ready to endure
一些最恶劣的条件
some of the harshest conditions
存在于地球上的。
that exist on planet Earth.
如此荒凉的极端
Such inhospitable extremes
不仅在两极发现。
are not only found at the poles.
随着海拔的升高...
As altitude increases...
..气温下降。
..temperatures fall.
在这里，动物也必须充分利用季节变化。
Here, too, animals must make the most of the sea
特别是当你准备好交配时。
Particularly if you're ready to mate.
一只雄性普通青蛙
A male common frog
在法国阿尔卑斯山。
in the French Alps.
他整个冬天都在冰下冬眠。
He has spent all winter hibernating under the ic
但现在是时候醒来了。
But now it's time to wake up.
他是冷血动物，需要阳光来温暖自己的身体。
Being cold-blooded, he needs the sun to warm his
但一旦几小时后开始
But once it sets in a few hours' time,
他可能会被冻死。
he could freeze to death.
所以找对象当务之急。
So finding a mate is urgent.
天气好。
The weather is good.
他开始滑雪橇。
And he starts to sledge.
但这不是一场独青蛙竞赛。
But this is not a one-frog race.
数十只正涌向繁殖池。
Dozens are rushing to the breeding pool.
山坡上有这么多青蛙...
This many frogs out on the slopes...
..不会被忽视。
..doesn't go unnoticed.
你买不起任何单据。
You can't afford any slips.
一切都很顺利。
It was all going so well.
做好了。
Made it.
青蛙呱呱叫
FROG CROAKS
但所有雌性都已经有了伴侣。
But all the females have already got partners.
只有一件事可以做到这一点。
There's only one thing for it.
摔角。
Wrestling.
这次不行。
Not this time.
Another latecomer.
一名女性。
A female.
她会是那个人吗？
Could she be the one?
有时迟到也会有回报。
Sometimes being late can pay off.
经过他的努力，雄性不会放过这个机会
After all his efforts, the male is not going to
从他的手指间溜走。
slip through his fingers.
这是北非阿特拉斯山脉的雪松林。
This is the cedar forest of the Atlas Mountains,
这些巴巴里猕猴度过了一个充实的夏天，
These Barbary macaques enjoyed a summer of plent
但现在他们正在付出代价。
but now they're paying the price.
这里的冬天可能很残酷。
Winter here can be brutal.
在某些年份，超过一半的群体死亡。
In some years, over half the group perish.
但在这个猕猴社会里，
But in this macaque society,
猴子越善于社交，
the more social the monkey,
生存的可能性就越大。
the more likely it is to survive.
通过挤在一起取暖可以使一切变得不同。
Keeping warm by huddling can make all the differ
但他们不能整天挤在一起。
But they can't huddle all day.
最终，它们必须分开进食。
They must, eventually, break apart to feed.
他们分散开来，寻找食物。
They spread out, searching for food.
但每天晚上，这群人都会回到雪松树丛中。
But each night, the group return to huddle in th
没有人愿意被排除在外。
No-one wants to be left out.
尤其是婴儿。
Especially the infants.
猕猴吱吱声
MACAQUE SQUEAKS
这个婴儿不知何故已经分开了。
This baby, somehow, has got separated.
他必须回到能救命的温暖的拥抱中，
He must get back to the life-saving warmth of th
等等。
and soon.
但有一个障碍。
But there is an obstacle.
脾气暴躁的雄性对婴儿的态度相当冷淡。
A grumpy male is giving the baby a rather cold s
成年猕猴的咕噜声
ADULT MACAQUE GRUNTS
婴儿猕猴的叫声
INFANT MACAQUE CHITTERS
也许是一种更微妙的方法。
Maybe a more subtle approach.
男子决定离开。
The male decides to leave.
终于...
At last...
..热情的接待。
..an enthusiastic reception.
男性的运气则较差。
The male has had less luck.
这可能是一个漫长的夜晚。
It could be a long night.
拥抱似乎是一种简单的爱意表达，
Huddling might seem a simple expression of affec
但对于这些猕猴来说，它对于生存至关重要。
but among these macaques it's essential for surv
而且不仅仅是这里。
And not just here.
5000英里外，在墨西哥的森林里，
5,000 miles away, in the forests of Mexico,
帝王蝶，以百万计，
monarch butterflies, in millions,
也为了生存而挤在一起。
also huddle for survival.
他们都曾穿越北美
All of them have travelled across North America
为了躲避即将到来的冬天。
to escape the winter that is coming there.
这片海拔3000米的森林，
This forest, at an altitude of 3,000 metres,
似乎并不能提供多少安慰……
might seem to offer little comfort...
..这里的气温可能会降至冰点以下，
..for temperatures here can drop below freezing,
这可能会杀死蝴蝶。
and that could kill the butterflies.
但事实上，有一层薄薄的暖空气
But in fact, a thin layer of warm air
被树冠困住可以保护他们，
trapped by the tree canopy protects them,
并且整个冬天都会这样做......
and will do so throughout the winter...
..前提是森林不受干扰。
..provided that the forest remains undisturbed.
然而，不可预测的极端天气
Unpredictable extremes of weather, however,
会破坏这种微妙的平衡。
can disrupt this delicate balance.
强风会深入森林，使空气变冷。
Strong winds can push deep into the forest, chil
阵风
WIND GUSTS
数十万只蝴蝶
Hundreds of thousands of butterflies
可能会从树枝上被吹下来。
may be blown from the branches.
在某些年份，暴风雨会杀死 75% 冬眠帝王蝶的生命。
In some years, storms kill 75% of hibernating mo
这个居然活下来了……
This one has survived...
..但在地面上。
..but on the ground.
夜间霜冻是致命的。
And night-time frosts are fatal.
它不能留在这里生活。
It can't stay here and live.
天太冷了，不能坐飞机
It is too cold to fly,
但它必须以某种方式回到树枝上。
but it must get back into the tree branches some
所以它开始爬升。
So it starts to climb.
这相当于一个人爬上摩天大楼。
It's the equivalent of a human climbing up a sky
安全，终于。
Safety, at last.
随着春天的到来，
As spring returns,
君主们从漫长的沉睡中醒来。
the monarchs wake from their long slumber.
现在地球上最伟大的自然奇观之一开始了。
And now starts one of the Earth's greatest natur
但这种大规模的觉醒正面临威胁。
But this mass awakening is under threat.
气候变化正在创造更多的极端天气，
The changing climate is creating more extreme we
风暴变得越来越频繁。
and storms are becoming more frequent.
但就目前而言，这一自然奇迹仍在继续。
But, for now, this miracle of nature continues.
火。
Fire.
不可预测且具有破坏性。
Unpredictable and destructive.
这是南非的fynbos。
This is South Africa's fynbos.
从植物学角度来说，它是地球上最多样化的栖息地之一......
Botanically one of the most diverse habitats on
..拥有超过 8,000 种不同的植物物种。
..with over 8,000 different plant species.
然而，每二十年，
Yet, every two decades,
火将植被烧成灰烬。
fire reduces the vegetation to ashes.
这看起来可能是灾难性的。
This may seem catastrophic.
但仅仅几天后，植物就焕发了生机……
But just days later, plants burst into life...
..并改变景观。
..and transform the landscape.
种子和球茎一直在等待这一事件。
Seeds and bulbs have been waiting for this event
与火一起经历了 9000 万年的进化
90 million years of evolution alongside fire
使一些植物如此紧密地适应
has made some plants so closely adapted
如果没有烟雾，它们就无法发芽。
that they can't germinate without the presence o
值得注意的是，地球上约 50% 的陆地栖息地
Remarkably, around 50% of planet Earth's terrest
依靠火来保持健康。
depend on fire to remain healthy.
在澳大利亚北部，这些大草原需要季节性火灾
In Northern Australia, these savannahs need seas
保持它们开放并防止附近森林蔓延。
to keep them open and prevent the spread of the
它们是重要的栖息地
And they are a vital habitat
对于这位色彩缤纷的居民。
for this colourful resident.
罕见的金肩鹦鹉。
The rare golden-shouldered parrot.
他和他的终生伴侣..
He and his lifelong partner..
食物都依赖草原...
rely on grassland for both food...
..和一个巢穴。
..and a nest site.
像往常一样，它们把卵产在白蚁丘的洞里。
As usual, they've laid their eggs in a hole in a
叽叽喳喳
CHIRPING
现在有四只小鸡了。
And now there are four chicks.
厚厚的泥墙不仅可以保护雏鸟免受捕食者的侵害，
The thick mud walls don't only protect chicks fr
但要使它们免受烈日的炎热。
but insulate them from the heat of the scorching
距离雏形仅剩几天，
With fledging just days away,
父母都在加班。
the parents are working overtime.
他们每天收集数千颗种子。
They collect thousands of seeds every day.
但他们有一个问题。
But they have a problem.
火灾季节变得越来越不规律。
The fire season is becoming more irregular.
如果他们还没有准备好起飞，
If they are not ready to fly,
小鸡们无处可逃。
chicks have no escape.
但选择在白蚁丘中筑巢有一个意想不到的好处。
But choosing to nest in a termite mound has a su
他们的家是防火的。
Their home is fireproof.
类似混凝土的墙壁可以保护小鸡免受外面火焰的伤害。
Concrete-like walls keep chicks safe from the fl
小鸡叽叽喳喳
CHICKS CHIRP
火草种子现在对鹦鹉来说更容易了
The seeds of fire grass are now easier for the p
在漆黑的大地上寻找……
to find on the blackened earth...
..它们是鹦鹉最喜欢的食物。
..and they are the parrots' favourite food.
所以，对于成年人和刚孵出的雏鸟来说......
So, for both adults and their fledgling chicks..
..火灾对于生存至关重要。
..fires are essential for survival.
但他们的草原家园正在缩小，
But their grassland home is shrinking,
这些可爱的鹦鹉中只剩下大约 1,000 只幸存。
and only about 1,000 of these lovely parrots sti
这是通过人类积极管理火灾
It's through the active management of fire by hu
他们的世界现在已经存在了。
that their world now exists at all.
人类正在影响地球上的栖息地。
Humans are affecting habitats across planet Eart
对于野生动物来说，很多时候，
For wildlife, all too often,
后果是灾难性的。
the consequences have been disastrous.
大象叫声
ELEPHANT CALLS
大象是最宽容的动物之一。
Elephants are among the most tolerant of animals
大象隆隆声
ELEPHANT RUMBLES
它们的寿命非常长，
They are very long-lived,
代际传递的知识使他们能够
and knowledge passed between generations enables
及时寻找食物和很少使用的水源
to find food and little-used sources of water in
面临着巨大的环境压力。
of great environmental stress.
但即使在大象中，
But even among elephants,
生存策略现在开始失败。
survival strategies are now beginning to fail.
在肯尼亚安博塞利，连年的极端天气，
In Amboseli, Kenya, years of extreme weather,
再加上家牛的过度放牧，
combined with overgrazing by domestic cattle,
正在把这些草原化为尘土。
are turning these grasslands to dust.
这位老太太已经40多岁了……
This matriarch is over 40 years old...
大象隆隆声
ELEPHANT RUMBLES
..她已经活了下来
..and she's already survived
东非一些最严重的干旱。
some of East Africa's worst droughts.
但今年，粮食严重短缺……
But this year, food is in extremely short supply
..她的家人正在努力寻找足够的食物。
..and her family are struggling to find enough.
她的小儿子营养不良，身体虚弱……
Her youngest son is malnourished and weak...
..并且落后于他的母亲和兄弟。
..and is lagging behind his mother and brother.
她带领他们来到一片她熟悉的金合欢树林。
She leads them to a pocket of acacia forest that
但折断的树枝和倒下的树木
But broken branches and fallen trees
表明其他大象已经到过这里。
show that other elephants have already been here
剩下的值得吃的已经所剩无几了。
There is very little left worth eating.
没有食物，他的母亲就无法产生足够的牛奶。
Without food, his mother cannot produce enough m
她别无选择……
She has no choice...
..但要留下她日渐衰弱的小腿......
..but to leave her weakening calf...
..并尝试在其他地方寻找食物。
..and try to find food elsewhere.
于是，她带着大儿子出发了……
So, she and her elder son head off...
..没有他。
..without him.
他只能希望他们能回来。
He can only hope for their return.
苍蝇嗡嗡声
FLIES BUZZ
但对于他来说，时间已经不多了。
But for him, time has run out.
没有什么是他的母亲或任何人，
There is nothing his mother, or anybody,
本来可以救他的。
could have done to save him.
低沉的隆隆声
LOW RUMBLING
在她的大儿子还活着的情况下，
With her elder son still alive,
她的家人还有希望。
there is hope for her family.
但前提是他们能够快速适应。
But only if they can adapt quickly.
事实证明，一些家庭具有很强的适应力。
Some families are proving to be resilient.
他们正在长途跋涉，远离安博塞利……
They're travelling long distances, away from Amb
..并寻找新的食物和水源。
..and finding new sources of food and water.
尽管干旱...
And despite the drought...
..小牛正在出生。
..calves are being born.
但鉴于变化的步伐
But given the pace of change
以及他们面临的挑战......
and the challenges they face...
..有多少非洲大象能够适应？
..how many of Africa's elephants will be able to
他们能做得足够快吗？
And can they do so fast enough?
戈壁滩。
The Gobi Desert.
一片沙地和雪地。
A land of sand and snow.
至少一百万年来，这一直是
For at least a million years, this has been
地球上最极端的栖息地之一。
one of the most extreme habitats on Earth.
然而沙滩上的脚印
Yet, footprints in the sand
揭示这里有生命。
reveal that there is life here.
一只雪豹。
A snow leopard.
很少见到...
Seldom seen...
..尤其是在如此炎热、干旱的条件下。
..especially in such hot, arid conditions.
它们生活在海拔2000米的地方，
They live up to 2,000 metres above sea level,
并巡逻广阔的领土。
and patrol vast territories.
他们很少在一起。
They are rarely seen together.
一个妈妈...
A mother...
..和幼崽。
..with cubs.
第一次在这里拍摄
Filmed here for the first time
在如此亲密的细节中。
in such intimate detail.
豹子咆哮
LEOPARDS SNARL
他们让我们一睹他们的家庭生活......
And they give us a glimpse of their family life.
..就这样。
..such as it is.
水研磨
WATER LAPPING
雪豹幼崽和妈妈待在一起
Snow leopard cubs stay with their mothers
比几乎所有其他大型猫科动物都长。
longer than those of almost any other big cat.
他们在一起已经两年多了……
They remain together for over two years...
..当他们学习如何应对极端情况时。
..as they learn how to master the extremes.
他们做得很好，因此能够蓬勃发展
Which they do so well that they are able to thri
在一些最热、最冷的地方...
in some of the hottest, coldest...
..以及地球上最高的地方。
..and highest places on Earth.
有些动物，经过数百万年，
Some animals, over millions of years,
已经进化出在极端恶劣条件下生存的方法。
have evolved ways of surviving extremely hostile
但随着极端变得更加极端......
But as the extremes become more extreme...
..进化正在被超越。
..evolution is being outpaced.
这些非凡的地方仍然有人居住
These extraordinary places are still inhabited
由地球上一些最具复原力的人
by some of Earth's most resilient
和适应性强的物种。
and adaptable species.
但在我们瞬息万变的世界中......
But in our rapidly changing world...
..这是地球，你可能再也见不到它了。
..this is planet Earth as you may never see it a
豹吼声
LEOPARD YOWLS
大卫·阿滕伯勒：地球上最极端的地方
DAVID ATTENBOROUGH: The most extreme parts of ou
并不总能在您期望的地方找到。
are not always found where you might expect.
隐藏在越南森林深处的一个当地人，
Hidden deep in the forests of Vietnam, a local m
何庆先生做出了非凡的发现。
Mr Ho Khanh, made an extraordinary discovery.
他当时并不知道，
He didn't know it at the time,
但他偶然发现了可以说是世界上最大的洞穴。
but he had stumbled upon arguably the largest ca
受到 Ho Khanh 先生的发现的启发，
Inspired by Mr Ho Khanh's discovery,
《行星地球》团队开始拍摄韩松洞。
the Planet Earth team set out to film Hang Son D
但首先，他们必须到达那里。
But first, they have to get there.
我们离开了河谷，
We've left the river valley,
我们现在正在上山到入口处。
and we're walking uphill now to the entrance.
这只是茂密的森林。
It's just thick, thick forest.
经过两天的艰苦跋涉，
After trekking for two gruelling days,
队伍终于到了。
the team finally arrive.
下面是韩松洞的入口，
Down here is the entrance to Hang Son Doong,
在这片巨大的丛林中这个小小的开口。
this tiny opening in this massive jungle.
令人惊奇的是居然有人发现了这个地方。
It's amazing that anyone ever found this place.
我们即将进入接下来的 18 天，
We're about to go in for the next 18 days,
从这里开始灯就亮了。
and it's lights on from here on out.
当地专家带领团队穿越黑暗。
Local experts guide the team through the darknes
好吧，我可以走了吗？
是的是的。
OK, I can go?  Yes, yes.
沉重的呼吸
HEAVY BREATHING
紧张地咯咯笑
NERVOUS CHUCKLING
我很好。
我可以。
I'm good. I'm OK.
实在是太滑了。
It's just really slippery.
复杂的绳索系统引导他们下降 90 米。
A complex system of ropes leads them down a 90-m
无线电喋喋不休
RADIO CHATTER
好的。
OK.
谢谢。
Thanks.
经过四个小时攀爬岩石......
After four hours clambering over rocks...
铁锅
PAN SIZZLING
......他们终于到达了他们的营地。
...they finally reach what will be their camp.
团队醒来，迎接新的一天——
The team wake to a new day -
但在黑暗中。
but in darkness.
卢克，你睡得怎么样？
How did you sleep, Luke?
相当疲惫。
Quite tired.
这些都是我身后的帐篷。
These are all of the tents behind me.
你可以看到他们很漂亮...
You can see they are pretty...
..非常舒适。
..pretty snug.
这是我们每天吃早餐的地方
This is where we have our breakfast every day,
由一些出色的厨师制作。
made by some amazing cooks.
这是我们的充电站。
This is our charging station.
相机设备的电池，我们的灯的电池，
Batteries for camera equipment, batteries for ou
我们的头灯，这非常重要。
our head torches, which are so important.
这是我们的水站。
This is our water station.
我们所拥有的一切都是有人带来的，
Everything that we have got has been brought in
所以你不能洗澡或洗澡。
so you can't shower or wash.
而且不仅仅是水。
And it's not just water.
成吨的设备必须搬进洞穴，
Tonnes of equipment has had to be carried into t
每一寸路。
every inch of the way.
现在在地下深处，强大的灯光
Now deep underground, the powerful lights
揭示这个洞穴有多么巨大。
reveal just how vast this cavern is.
这是惊人的。
That is amazing.
看那个。
它是...
Look at that. It's...
它超大！
It's huge!
当你打开每一盏灯时，
As you turn on each of the lights,
这个巨大房间的另一部分显露出来。
another part of this enormous chamber is reveale
这是魔法。
绝对神奇。
It's magic. Absolutely magic.
为了尝试捕捉真实的比例，
To try and capture the true scale,
该团队尝试了一种以前从未尝试过的拍摄技术。
the team attempt a filming technique never tried
我们正在尝试与无人机一起跳舞，
We're trying to do a little bit of a dance with
我们的一架无人机略低于另一架，
whereby we have one drone sort of slightly below
一个在拍摄，另一个在洞穴中照明。
one filming the other one lighting a feature in
这是一个非常狭窄的空间。
It's a really tight space.
你什么也看不见。
You can't see anything.
可能会出什么问题？
What could go wrong?
无人机嗡嗡声
DRONE BUZZES
好吧，慢一点。
OK, slow down a bit.
这让大家都有些紧张。
It's making everyone a little nervous.
是的，卢克，别再往上爬了。
Yeah, don't go up any higher, Luke.
好吧，这个高度不错。
OK, that's a nice height.
用一架无人机照明和一架无人机拍摄......
With one drone lighting and one drone filming...
..它们揭示了一些世界上最大的石笋的奇迹。
..they reveal the wonder of some of the world's
日子一天天过去，团队逐渐适应
As the days pass, the team settle into
地下生活的日常生活。
the everyday routine of life underground.
这就是脱离电网的缩影。
This is the epitome of being off-grid.
我们称之为跷跷板厕所
We call that one seesaw loo
因为它有点像在岩石上
because it's kind of on a rock,
每次你坐在上面并向后靠时，
and every time you sit on it and lean back,
你害怕会有灾难发生。
you're scared that there's going to be a disaste
最奇怪的是没有联系
The strangest thing is having no connection
对外界的任何事情。
to the outside world whatsoever.
时间被扭曲了。
地下没有任何意义。
Time is warped. Nothing makes sense underground.
在没有日光的情况下，团队昼夜不停地工作
Without daylight to guide them, the team work ro
捕捉洞穴最独特的特征。
to capture the cave's most unique features.
最特别的是，
Most special of all,
一年只发生几周的事件。
an event which happens only a few weeks a year.
为了到达那里，他们必须导航
To get there, they must navigate
穿过巨石场和狭窄的挤压。
through boulder fields and tight squeezes.
BLEEP
大约五十万年前，这里
Here, around half a million years ago,
洞顶塌陷，
the cave roof collapsed,
打开一扇通向外面世界的窗户。
opening a window to the outside world.
团队等待合适的条件。
The team wait for just the right conditions.
我们已经在这里坐了好几个小时了。
We've been sat here for hours.
最后，就在墙的右侧，
And finally, just on the right-hand side of the
我们可以看到最初的曙光。
we can see the first signs of light.
经过几周的黑暗
After weeks of darkness
地下200米...
200 metres underground...
..他们看到阳光
..they see sunlight
照亮洞穴地面。
illuminate the cave floor.
它照亮这个巨大洞穴的方式......
The way it just lights up this massive cave...
..当我们尝试用大约四到五个灯来做到这一点时
..when we've been trying to do it with about fou
甚至几乎无法照亮最小的部分。
and barely even lighting the smallest section.
当阳光照进来的时候，它只是...
When the sun comes in, it just...
他泡芙
HE PUFFS
我想每个人都起鸡皮疙瘩了。
I think everyone's got goose bumps.
我想我一生中从未如此欣赏过阳光。
I don't think I've ever appreciated sun so much
太不可思议了。
It's incredible.
看看背光的瀑布。
Look at the backlit waterfalls.
他们下来的速度真慢。
They're so slow coming down.
这确实是我见过的最好的事情之一。
It's literally one of the best things I've ever
对于船员来说，阳光标志着深刻的结束
For the crew, the sunbeam marks a profound end
他们在山洞里的时光。
to their time in the cave.
我们在外面！
We're outside!
它是那么绿，那么亮。
It's so green, it's so bright.
回到地面感觉就像我们所属的地方。
Being back above ground feels like where we belo
想象一下还有什么其他极端情况真是令人惊奇
It's a wonder to imagine what other extremes
仍然位于地球表面之下。
still lie beneath the surface of planet Earth.
下次...
Next time...
..人类世界..
..the human world...
..动物必须找到新的生存方式......
..where animals must find new ways to survive...
..在我们中间。
..amongst us.
栖息地探索者让动物及其栖息地栩栩如生。
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habita
探索这个免费的互动，并制作折纸动物。
Explore this free interactive, and make origami
访问 bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
并点击开放大学的链接。
and follow the links to the Open University.
或者要订购免费印刷版，请访问网站
Or to order a free printed version, visit the we
或拨打屏幕上的号码。
or call the numbers on the screen.